Guide to the Burt Green Wilder papers, 1841-1925
Wilder, Burt Green papers, 1841-1925
- Excerpts from newspapers and other writings re the River's Causeway, South Carolina battle., July 2, 1864 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Army Medical Museum Items., 1914-1916 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Alleged murders of captured Black soldiers by Confederate troops. Referred to in "Reminiscences of the Civil War," by John Hallum. (A former Confederate soldier.), 1903 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Treatment of soldiers during the Civil War., 1864-65 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Recollections of life as a Civil War medical cadet at Judiciary Square Hospital, Washington, D.C., 1862-1863 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Recollections of the USA General Hospital on Judiciary Square, Washington, D.C. (BGW as a medical cadet)., June, 1862-June, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Private Joseph Parsons, Company F, 2nd Maryland Infantry. (Account of injuries at Bull Run)., Aug. 29, 1863 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- "Calendar of main events - national - regimental - personal," Wilder's own title for record book, mostly blank., June 1863 - September 1865 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Letters from students to Burt Green Wilder., 1885?, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Tale of the University Bear on the C.U. campus (by BGW). The bear was for a long time under the care of John H. Comstock while he was a student at Cornell., Nov. 1883 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Correspondence with publishers., 1913-1917 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Adjutant and Inspector - General's Office, Woodstock Vermont. Register of Commissioned Officers of the Vermont Volunteers in the Service of the U.S., June 1863 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Burt Green Wilder's Diary (typescript in 1910). pp. 1-50., 1863 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  This is a photocopy of the original found in Box 9.
- Burt Green Wilder's Diary (typescript in 1910). pp. 51-100., 1863-1864 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Burt Green Wilder's Diary (typescript in 1910). pp. 101-150., 1864 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Burt Green Wilder's Diary (typescript in 1910). pp. 151-200., 1864-1865 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Burt Green Wilder's Diary (typescript in 1910). pp. 201-241., 1865 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- The Federal government and segregation. (newspaper clippings)., 1914 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Various newspaper clippings re the Civil War., 1912-1916 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- "The Week in the War." (newspaper clippings)., 1914 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Excerpts from [UNK] review of Dr. R.W. Shufeldt: America's Greatest Problem: The Negro., 1915 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Articles on Brains and Skulls., 1892-1895 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Book notices and reviews of "Anatomical Technology as applied to the Domestic Cat" by BGW and Simon Henry Gage., 1882 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Pamphlets on Insects, Birds, Bats, Monkeys and others., 1868-1872 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Medical pamphlets, 1868-1889 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Fragments of articles from medical journals., 1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Conference on the conditions of American Negroes., June, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Mutilation and burning alive of Eli Persons, (a black man) in Memphis, Tennessee; BGW's interest in the case., May 22, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Clippings from Ithaca Journal and Cornell Daily Sun. BGW's lectures on Military Science., 1895, 1909 1912 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Clippings re the film "Birth of a Nation," and the play, "The Clansman.", 1915 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- "Vivisection in the state of New York." (Written by BGW.) Article reprint., June, 1883 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Harper's New Monthly Magazine., Nov. 1869 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Articles appearing in the Atlantic Monthly Magazine. "Time Works Wonders," "Right and Left," and "Equal yet Diverse.", 1870 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Clippings from The Cornell Daily Sun., 1881-1895, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- One journal: The Sanitarian. Vol. XII. No. 174., May, 1884 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- "Food and Morals." A sermon by Rev. J.F. Clymer, First M.E. Church of Auburn, New York., June 20, 1888 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Annual Report of the Trustees of the Museum of Comparative Zoology. Report of the Director., 1866-67, 1893-94 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Articles re the resignation of William C. Russel from Cornell University., May 21, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Experiments and study of anatomy of cats and other animals by BGW. All newspaper clippings., 1880-82 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Burt Green Wilder's views of Secret Societies., Oct. 22, 1873 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- "The Living Death" (an anti-drug use pamphlet by Dr. H.H. Kane.), May, 1883 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Medical pamphlets in German., 1894 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Medical pamphlets in French and Italian., c. 1897 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Medical reports on Alcoholics and Alcoholism., 1886-1888 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- "The House that Jack Built," a poem written by George Shepard Burleigh, and hand copied by BGW., 1868 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- "Darwinism in Ethics." A lecture given by W.M. Salter., Mar. 17, 1887 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- American Public Health Association Lomb Prize Essays. (Four volumes)., 1886 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Report of the Ann Arbor Meeting of the American Association of the Advancement of Science., 1885 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- 1. Ruttan Heating and Ventilating Company, Bloomington, Ill. "Cut [i.e. cutaway drawing of house] representing the Ruttan System of warming and ventilation, with Hawley's improvements." R.R. Donnelley, Lakeside Press, printer; Bond & Chandler, engravers [undated, folded, colored diagram, ca. 26" x 22"]. 2. "A new idea in architecture": undated journal article with floor plan and illustration, describing a modern, healthful apartment building 3. Photo of unidentified clapboard house (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Original Typescript Diary of BGW 1862-1865 (Box 9)
  Do not use this original, it is fragile. Use the photocopy found in Box 7.
- Phrenology Materials, 1872, 1879, and 1897 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Phrenology Materials, 1898 and 1913 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Phrenology Materials, 1905-1905 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Phrenology Materials, 1909-1910 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- News Clippings, Essays, Course Description. 1874, 1879, 1881, 1888, and Undated, 1874-1888 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- News Clippings, Booklets, Ca. 1880s (Box 10, Folder 6)
- News Clippings, 1895-1899 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- News Clippings, 1900-1907 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- News Clippings, 1908-1912 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- News Clippings, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- News Clippings, 1914-1925 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- News Clippings, 1929-1930 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Old Ironsides Clippings (Music), 1906, 1911-1913, 1916-1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Old Ironsides, Bulletins, 1911-1913, 1916, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Old Ironsides (Music), 1912, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Old Ironsides (Music), 1912, 1916, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Ode to Lifesavers, Peacemaker, Dr. Hooker (Music), 1907, 1909, 1911, 1914, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Clippings Related to Nantucket (Music), 1885-1916 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Clippings Related to Nantucket (Music), 1885-1916 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- County Guy (Music), 1917 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Founder's Centenary Hymn, Fiat Justitia, 1897, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Fiat Justitia (Music), 1904, 1911, 1915, 1925 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Fiat Justitia (Music), 1910-1912 (Box 10, Folder 23)
- Home Song, Thanatopsis, Last Night (Music), 1909, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 24)
- Largo, Newsclippings, 1905, 1911-1912, 1915, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 25)
- Largo (Music), 1909, 1913, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1901, 1903-1905, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1903, 1909, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1904-1911 (Box 10, Folder 29)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1905-1906, 1908-1909 (Box 10, Folder 30)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1905, 1907, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1905, 1907, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 32)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1905, 1908-1911, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1905, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1914, 1916-1917 (Box 10, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous Music, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 36)
- Photographs and Portraits, Dr. Oliver Wendell Holmes (printed, not original), John Townsend Trowbridge, "Six Great Authors", (Unidentified composite engraving), 1894, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 37)
- Field Family Genealogy, 1901, 1906-1908, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 38)
- Oliver Wendell Holmes News Clippings. 1894, 1896, 1900, 1902, 1909, 1916, 1932, 1894-1932 (Box 10, Folder 39)
- Unidentified graphics, 2 color landscapes, 1 engraving of ships., Undated (Box 10, Folder 40)
- Draft of B. G. Wilder's Biography of Holmes and Notes Concerning Publication, Ca.1910-1920 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Clippings and Notes Relating to the Spider and Silk Producing Spiders, 1856-1920 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Papers Published about the Spider, 1865, 1866, 1900, 1903, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Papers Published about the Spider, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Clippings and Notes about the Spider, Ca. 1850s-1910s (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Hygiene and Morality Leaflet and Poem by Ruth Putnam, Ca. 1890s (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Notes on Health, Ca. 1890s (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Diaries, 1866-1869 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 1870-1875 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Diaries, 1877-1882 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Diaries, 1883-1889 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Diaries, 1890-1895 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Diaries, 1896-1903 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1904-1909 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1910-1913 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Diaries, 1914-1918 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Diaries, 1919-1920 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Louis Agassiz, clippings, Wilder's notes about Agassiz, 1860-1868 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Louis Agassiz, includes printed copy of his will, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Louis Agassiz, 1870-1872 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Louis Agassiz, printed photo of him at blackboard, 1873, 1873-1874 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Louis Agassiz, 1883-1885 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Louis Agassiz, 1883, 1908-1909, 1911, 1918-1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Louis Agassiz, 1886-1997 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Louis Agassiz, 1898-1899 (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Louis Agassiz, 1902-May 1907 (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Louis Agassiz, June-Sept. 1907 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Louis Agassiz, Ca. 1910s (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Cornell University, schedule of subjects Spring Term 1872, general courses of study, October 1868, 1868-1891 (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Cornell University, including photos of McGraw Hall, cyanotype and sepia, 1893-1922 (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Etiquette, Health and Hygiene Article, Correspondence, and Leaflets, (1875-1876, 1882, 1886-1889, 1893-1894, 1905, Bulk 1889), 1875-1905 (Box 12, Folder 19)
- Hygiene, Physiology, and other Professional Notes, 1875, 1897, 1902, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Requests to Attend Lectures and Lecture Tickets, 1866-1915 (Bulk 1897) (Box 12, Folder 21)
- The Wilder Quarter-Century Book, 1893-1894, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 22)
- University Related Articles (Cornell and others), 1887, 1889, 1915 (Bulk 1889) (Box 12, Folder 23)
- Anatomy Manuscripts, microscope instructions, 1872, 1882, 1892 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Bone (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Brain (Black and White) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Brain (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Cat Dissection (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Chimpanzee Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Dissection Equipment (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Dissection Photograph, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Heart (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Animal Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous Dissection (Cyanotype) Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Photograph of unidentified office with table, desk, books, lab equipment, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Small Anatomy Photographs, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Caged Cat Photograph, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Brain Collection Photographs, Ca. 1880s (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Brain Collection Photographs, Ca. 1880s (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Anatomy Sketches (Miscellaneous), Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Anatomical Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Bone Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Brain Sketch with Commentary, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Brain Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Cat Dissection Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Dissection Equipment Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Dissection Equipment Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Frog Anatomy Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Heart Sketches, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Printed dissection manual, unidentified, (Muscles, Viscera, Blood Vessels), Pages 204-368, mounted on pages in an album, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Printed dissection manual, unidentified, continued, (Lymphatics, Nervous System, Cranial Nerves, Organs of Sense, Bibliography, Index), Pages 364-575, Ca. 1870s-1890s (Box 16)
- Bound volume with names on spine, Agassiz, Dana, Gray, Parsons, Wyman. Contains primarily journal articles responding to Darwin's Origin of Species, and other articles on species. Includes James D. Dana's "Thoughts on Species", 1857, "The Arwinian Theory Consistent with Christianity", lecture by Dr. McCosh, Princeton., 1860-1868 (Box 16)
- Bound volume with title, "Homology of Limbs", includes printed articles, manuscripts, notes, and letters on anatomy., 1863-1867 (Box 16)
- Agassiz' Lectures, 1868 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Biographical Material: College, 1861 and ca. 1918 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Biographical Material: Compositions and Sketches, 1857-1859 and 1895 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Biographical Material: Cornell Classes, 1868-1869 and 1892-1893 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Biographical Material: Pets, 1924 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Biographical Material: Reminiscences, 1898, 1909-1912, ca.1913-1925 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Re: Estate of Burt G. Wilder, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Family Register, 1841 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Retirement of Burt G. Wilder, 1910 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Four bound volumes. 1. "Tableau synoptique du cerveau, cervelet, et moelle epiniere" (from *Anatomie clastique du docteur Auzoux*): manuscript key/ index in unidentified hand. 2. Volume with spine title: "Nomenclature--papers & notes by B. G. Wilder" reprints bound together with mss. notes; includes a blank "Brain Bequest" form near back of volume. 3. "Records of the High-School Scrap-Book for the year commencing Sept. 1858" editors Burt G. Wilder and Miss Fannie W.(?) Chandler. 4. Volume with spine title: "Papers by G. Wilder": includes typed letters and printed articles. (Box 18)
- Printing block, microscope slides (Box 22)
- Wilder family Bible, One volume, plus one newspaper clipping. [Old Testament, New Testament, and Apocrypha], published by Mathew Carey, Philadelphia, 1809 with inscriptions: Leominster, February 8, 1813; property of David Wilder, Jun. (given to him by his father, David Wilder, Sr., who had received it from his own father) The family record is written on p. 677-80, between the O.T. and the Apocrypha plus newspaper clipping: "Religions of the Presidents" (Box 23)
- Right Ulna bone fragments of Daniel P. Havey of 19th Mass. Infantry Regiment (with shot), 1862; MU-1391 (Box 29)
  "Parts of the right ulna of Dan'l P. Havey, Co. I, 19th Mass. Resected by Dr. Brown, July 1862. Good recovery; useful arm; work in Charlestown Rope Walk."
- Spider Specimens (Fragile glass frame), ca. 1870s-1890s; MU-1392 (Box 25)
- Spider Specimen, ca. 1870s-1890s; MU-1393 (Box 25)
- Spider Specimen, ca. 1870s-1890s; MU-1394 (Box 25)
- Silk Specimen - 2 mile strand, ca. 1870s-1890s; MU-1395 (Box 25)
- Papers in the Family Bible, 1836, 1841, 1856 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Papers on Family Background; Edward Marshall, David, and Harris Wilder, etc; Small Book of Wilder Family Clippings (Box 26, Folder 2)
  Includes ca. 1890s-1900s, 1910, 1913-1914, and 1917
- Prepared Autobiography (1911) and Related Letters and Wilder Clippings (Box 26, Folder 3)
  Includes 1869, 1893, 1903, 1905, 1907, 1909-1912, 1915, and 1917
- Bibliography of Wilder Publications and List of Papers, 1861-ca.1911 (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Photocopies of typescript diaries, manuscripts and correspondence. (Box 27)
- "Report on Wilder Brain Collection", by Hedwig Kasprzak, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 1)
- "The Brain of Helen H. Gardner", by James W. Papez, 1927 (Box 28, Folder 2)
- How to make a brain bequest, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 2)
- Copy of Burt G. Wilder's will, 1924 (Box 28, Folder 4)
- Five Certificates awarded to Burt Green Wilder, 1859, 1865, 1869, 1881 (Map-case BB-25)
- Photographs, Portraits of BGW's military and medical colleagues during the Civil War (original cabinet card photographs, unless otherwise noted); two small photos of Civil War battle sites in South Carolina; one record-book [Descriptive captions based on Wilder's own notes]
  - J. F. (James Forster) Alleyne Adams (1844-1914) Intimate friend of Wilder's; acting Medical Cadet in Wash., DC Photo by: Warren, Lamson's Block, Cambridgeport, MA; 4.25" x 2.5" [housed together], 1862-1863 (Box 19, Folder 1, 1a)
  - Maj. John W. M. Appleton saw action at Fort Wagner, Morris Island, S. Carolina (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - William Francis Bartlett (1840-1876) Major-General at age 24 Engineer with ? engraving of his statue in Pittsfield, Mass. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - John R. Bowles (African American) 2nd Chaplain of the 55th Mass; d. Sept. 3, 1874 Photo by: Matthews, Piqua, OH; 6.5" x 4.25" (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Dr. John Hill Brinton Surgeon, U.S. Vols.; In 1862—63 charged with preparing Surgical History of the War; died March, 1907 (printed, not original photo) (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Francis Henry Brown, Surgeon at Judiciary Square Hospital, Wash., D. C. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Lieut. Henry Camp (mounted clipping from Colliers, NY Weekly by Walter Camp; with printed photos of BGW and Robert Gould Shaw) (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sergt. William Harvey Carney (African American) Co. C, 54th Mass.; holding flag he saved at Fort Wagner, Morris Island, S. Carolina 6.5" x 4.75" (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Chandler family of Brookline, Mass. (clipping from the Brookline Chronicle, Dec. 7, 1918, which contains photos of Chandler family members who fought in the Civil War and WWI; includes Lieut. Col. Charles Lyon Chandler of the 57th Mass. Regiment, killed in action, 1864; was a schoolmate of BGW (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Col. John L. Clem youngest soldier to serve with the Union Army (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 2nd. Lieut. Thomas Murrett DeLorme Confederate; Blake's Battery (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - _____ DeLorme, son of 2nd. Lieut. Thomas M. DeLorme (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Orderly Sergt. William H. Dupree (African American) Co. H, 55th Mass.; for many years in charge of South End Station of the Boston Post Office 7.25" x 5.0" (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Capt. Luis F. Emilio Commander of Co. E, 54th. Mass. Vol. Infantry Regiment author of *A Brave Black Regiment; the history of the 54th Mass.* printed photo from journal, not original; 4.25" x 3.0" (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Rev. James H. Fowler Chaplain of the First South Carolina Colored Infantry; was a student of Divinity and Zoology at Harvard, 1862 2 photos, by: G. H. Loomis, Boston (as young man), 4.25” x 2.5” Metcalf, Boston (as older man), 6.5" x 4.25" (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Lt. Col. Charles Barnard Fox, Dorchester, Mass. 3rd Commander of the 55th Mass.; Brevet Col. of U.S. Vols.; commanded the 55th at Rivers' Causeway, July 2, 1864. Later a member of Mass. State Legislature; died March 30, 1895 2 photos, by: Notman, Boston & Cambridge; 6.5" x 4.25" (1895) and J. W. Black & Co., n.p.; 6.5" x 4.25" (n.d.) (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Capt. Frank Goodwin Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.; with the 55th later photo (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Augustus A. Gould, M.D. (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Dr. George Milbry Gould, with his autograph. Inventor of bifocal lens eyeglasses Photo by: F. Gutekunst, Philadelphia, August 10, 1922 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Robert W. Gourdine (African American); with his autograph note to BGW former slave; soldier with the 55th Mass.; became station-master on Fitchburg RR. (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - James Manter Greenleaf seated, white-bearded man, with head-covering that appears to be evidence of a past injury; his name appears on verso (accompanied by another photo of an unidentified younger man standing, in uniform; verso reads: "Please return to James Manter Greenleaf, Stark, Maine") (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Col. Norwood Penrose Hallowell, of Philadelphia First Commander of the 55th Mass.; wounded at Antietam. later president of the National Bank of Commerce died at West Medford, Apr. 11, 1914 6.5" x 4.75" (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Dr. William A. Hammond Surgeon General of the United States (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Col. Alfred Stedman Hartwell later, Brig. Gen. of 55th Mass. (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Lieut. William G. Hinson 7th S. C. Cavalry; born on James Island, S.C.; "A fine example of the southern soldier and courteous gentleman." 8.0" x 6.0" (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Maj. John Johnson Confederate engineer; in charge of engineering part of Fort Sumter; later Episcopal clergyman (engraved portrait, 6.0" x 5.5") (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - 1st Lieut. Dennis Hartwell Jones Co. 1, 55th Mass. (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Rev. Frederick N. Knapp, Brookline, Mass. 1862-63, agent of the Sanitary Commission in Washington; Unitarian clergyman, 1887 (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - William H. Lathrop Asst. Surgeon, 55fth Mass. (later photo; with newspaper clipping) (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - David Lee (African American) Pvt., Co. C, 55th Mass.; “Served for a time as my orderly. Absolutely trustworthy.” Later worked in Xenia, Ohio (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Dr. Elias J. Marsh Asst. Surgeon, in charge of Judiciary Square Hospital, Wash., DC photo by: W. Kurtz, NY (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - William Mather Confederate gunner of DeLorme's section of artillery at River's Causeway, James Island, S.C. 7.75" x 3.75" (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Dr. James R. May, 1862-63, of Portsmouth, N.H. Medical cadet in Judiciary Square Hospital, 1862-63. 4.0" x 2.5'' (plus modern surrogate print of original cabinet card photo) (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - "Mitt" dog found on battlefield, (2 cc.), ca. 1864 (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Robert T. Morris (Box 19, Folder 35)
  - Jimmy Noland drummer boy photo by: Peln & Co., Wash., DC; 4.0" x 2.5" (Box 19, Folder 36)
  - Lt. Col. William Nutt, of Natick, Mass. Capt., Major and Lt. Col. of Co. C, 55th Mass.; Brevet Col. .S. Vols.; died Aug. 31,1909 photo by: Henry Barrett, Cambridge, MA; 6.5" x 4.25" (Box 19, Folder 37)
  - Major Frank Oakley, ca. 1900-1910s 1st Lieut., Co. K, Seventh Wisconsin Inf’y. Wounded Aug. 23, 1862 at Rappahannock Station, Va.; tended by his wife, BGW, and Dr. Francis H. Brown later, clerk of U.S. District Court, Madison with photo of Mrs. Frank Oakley, ca. 1900-1910s; both 11” x 11” (Box 19, Folder 38)
  - Charles Page Surgeon and Brigadier General in charge of Judiciary Square Hospital when BGW was there, 1862-63 (Box 19, Folder 39)
  - Calvin Pratt (1842-1911), as older man, Medical Cadet at Judiciary Square Hospital, 1862-63 (Box 19, Folder 40)
  - Mrs. Col. David Price, of Newport, RI; with her dog; picture postcard, ca. 1890s (Box 19, Folder 41)
  - Dr. Joseph Trimble Rothrock fellow student of BGW at Harvard; capt. in a Penn. regiment; wounded at Fredericksburg; BGW removed a ball from his leg photo of him as a young man, by: Henry Ulke, Wash., DC; 4.25" x 2.5" two additional photos: another as a young man; another (printed, not original) as an older man (Box 19, Folder 42)
  - Col. Robert Gould Shaw, Commander of the 54th Mass. Regiment 3 printed, not original photos (two are on same page as Lieut. Henry Camp) (Box 19, Folder 43)
  - Carleton A. Shurtleff son of the Brookline Shurtleff photo by: Warren, Lowell, MA; 4.25" x 2.0" (Box 19, Folder 44)